Theodore Roosevelt Jr. Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Theodore Roosevelt Jr. Papers 1780-1962 1920-1944
MSS38281
Roosevelt, Theodore, Jr., 1887-1944
25,000 items
77 containers
33 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Army officer, author, and public official. Correspondence, memoranda, diaries, drafts of speeches and writings, subject files, newspaper clippings, and other papers pertaining chiefly to Roosevelt's service as United States assistant secretary of the navy (1921-1924) under Warren G. Harding and Secretary of the Navy Edwin Denby, as governor of Puerto Rico (1929-1932), and as governor general of the Philippines (1932-1933).
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Alsop, Joseph, 1910-1989--Correspondence.; Alsop, Stewart--Correspondence.; Borah, William Edgar, 1865-1940--Correspondence.; Buck, Pearl S. (Pearl Sydenstricker), 1892-1973--Correspondence.; Chiang, Kai-shek, 1887-1975--Correspondence.; Coolidge, Calvin, 1872-1933--Correspondence.; Denby, Edwin, 1870-1929.; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969--Correspondence.; Frankfurter, Felix, 1882-1965--Correspondence.; Frost, Robert, 1874-1963--Correspondence.; Hanna, Marcus Alonzo, 1837-1904--Correspondence.; Harding, Warren G. (Warren Gamaliel), 1865-1923--Correspondence.; Harding, Warren G. (Warren Gamaliel), 1865-1923.; Hilles, Charles Dewey, 1867-1949--Correspondence.; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964--Correspondence.; Knox, Frank, 1874-1944--Correspondence.; Lindsay, Vachel, 1879-1931--Correspondence.; Lippmann, Walter, 1889-1974--Correspondence.; MacArthur, Douglas, 1880-1964--Correspondence.; Marshall, George C. (George Catlett), 1880-1959--Correspondence.; Maugham, W. Somerset (William Somerset), 1874-1965--Correspondence.; Pershing, John J. (John Joseph), 1860-1948--Correspondence.; Pinchot, Gifford, 1865-1946--Correspondence.; Quezon, Manuel Luis, 1878-1944--Correspondence.; Roosevelt family--Correspondence.; Roosevelt, Eleanor Butler, 1888-1960. Eleanor Butler Roosevelt papers.; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962--Correspondence.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945--Correspondence.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Roosevelt, Kermit, 1889-1943--Correspondence.; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919--Correspondence.; Roosevelt, Theodore, Jr., 1887-1944.; Root, Elihu, 1845-1937--Correspondence.; Smith, Alfred Emanuel, 1873-1944.; Stimson, Henry L. (Henry Lewis), 1867-1950--Correspondence.; Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951--Correspondence.; White, Walter, 1893-1955--Correspondence.; White, William Allen, 1868-1944--Correspondence.; Wood, Leonard, 1860-1927.; Woollcott, Alexander, 1887-1943--Correspondence.
Organizations
American Legion.; Conference on the Limitation of Armament (1921-1922: Washington, D.C.); Philippines. Gobernador-General.; Puerto Rico. Governor.; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ); United States. Office of the Assistant Secretary of the Navy.
Subjects
Disarmament.; Military pensions--United States.; Military readiness.; Outdoor life.; Political campaigns--United States.; Politics, Practical--United States.; Prohibition.; Socialism.; Travel.; Veterans--United States.; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1939-1945.
Places
Africa--Description and travel.; East Asia--Description and travel.; New York (State)--Politics and government.; United States--Intellectual life--20th century.; United States--Politics and government--1901-1953.; United States--Social conditions.
Occupations
Army officers.; Authors.; Public officials.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Theodore Roosevelt Jr., assistant secretary of the navy during the administration of Warren G. Harding, army officer, author, and political aspirant, were given to the Library of Congress by his heirs, 1958-1964.
Transfers
Photographic negatives and prints have been transferred to the Library's Prints and Photographs Division where they are identified as part of these papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Theodore Roosevelt Jr. are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1887, Sept. 13 Born, Oyster Bay, N.Y.
1908 A.B., Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass.
1910 Married Eleanor Butler Alexander (died 1960)
1910 1917 Engaged in business
1917, June Arrived in France with the U.S. Army's First Division, American Expeditionary Forces
1918 Promoted to lieutenant colonel
1919 Helped organize the American Legion Published Average Americans (New York: G.P. Putnam's Sons. 252 pp.)
1919 1920 Member, New York State Assembly
1921 1924 Assistant secretary of the navy
1922 Chairman, Committee of Naval Experts at Limitation of Armament Conference
1924 Republican candidate for governor of New York
1925 1926 Led James Simpson-Roosevelt Asiatic expedition
1926 Published with Kermit Roosevelt East of the Sun and West of the Moon (New York: C. Scribner's Sons. 284 pp.)
1928 Published Rank and File; True Stories of the Great War (New York: C. Scribner's Sons. 279 pp.)
1928 1929 Led Kelley-Roosevelt-Field Museum expedition, Asia
1929 Published All In the Family (New York: G.P. Putnam's Sons. 189 pp.) Published with Kermit Roosevelt Trailing the Giant Panda (New York: C. Scribner's Sons. 278 pp.)
1929 1932 Governor, Puerto Rico
1932 1933 Governor General, the Philippines
1933 Published with Harold J. Coolidge Three Kingdoms of Indo-China (New York: Thomas Y. Crowell. 331 pp.)
1934 1935 Chairman of the Board, American Express Co.
1935 Vice president, Doubleday, Doran and Co.
1937 Published Colonial Policies Of the United States (Garden City, N.Y.: Doubleday, Doran. 204 pp.)
1941 Returned to active duty in the U.S. Army; promoted to brigadier general
1944, July 12 Died in France
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Theodore Roosevelt Jr. (1887-1944), which include correspondence and other papers of his wife Eleanor Butler Roosevelt, cover the period 1780-1962, bulking largest between 1920 and 1944. The collection consists of Diaries, Family Correspondence, General Correspondence, Special Correspondence, Letters of Condolence and Congratulation, Subject File, Speech, Article, and Book File, Printed Matter, and Papers of Theodore Roosevelt (1858-1919). The last segment of the papers contains correspondence of President Theodore Roosevelt, including nine letters addressed to Marcus Alonzo (Mark) Hanna.
Theodore Roosevelt, Jr., was not a consistent diarist. However, the diaries he did maintain, written primarily during the 1920s, are significant for their observations on important events and individuals. There are numerous entries concerning his activities as assistant secretary of the navy and his relationships with Secretary of the Navy Edwin Denby, President Warren G. Harding, and others. The diaries, which are handwritten as well as in typescript, contain notations and deletions made by Eleanor Roosevelt after her husband's death.
Roosevelt maintained a large correspondence with family members, often writing diary-like letters. Other significant family correspondence includes the letters he exchanged with his father concerning political events, particularly after 1903.
Correspondence of Theodore and Eleanor Butler Roosevelt with prominent associates and friends is contained chiefly in the Special Correspondence series. Among their numerous correspondents are Joseph and Stewart Alsop, William Edgar Borah, Pearl S. Buck, Chiang Kai-shek, Calvin Coolidge, Dwight D. Eisenhower, Felix Frankfurter, Robert Frost, Edward Grey, Warren G. Harding, Charles Dewey Hilles, Herbert Hoover, Frank Knox, Vachel Lindsay, Walter Lippmann, Douglas MacArthur, George C. Marshall, W. Somerset Maugham, John J. Pershing, Gifford Pinchot, Manuel Luis Quezon, Eleanor Roosevelt, Franklin D. Roosevelt, Elihu Root, Henry Lewis Stimson, Arthur H. Vandenberg, Walter Francis White, William Allen White, and Alexander Woollcott.
The General Correspondence and the Subject File contain much information about social, political, and intellectual currents in the 1920s and 1930s. Prohibition, military preparedness, "Cousin Franklin" (Franklin D. Roosevelt), political campaigns, socialism, and veterans' benefits are among the topics discussed. As a government official, military officer, and son of a former president, Theodore Roosevelt, Jr., received letters from ordinary citizens as well as prominent individuals. These letters and Roosevelt's replies constitute a rich source of information about the period.
Among the major facets of Roosevelt's career that are documented in the Subject File are his activities in organizing the American Legion in 1919; his role in the presidential election campaign of Leonard Wood, 1919-1920; his participation in the Washington Conference on the Limitation of Armament, 1921-1922; his race against Alfred Emanuel Smith for the governorship of New York, 1924; his expeditions to Africa and the Far East, 1924-1939; and his military participation in both world wars, which led to numerous medals and decorations, including the Croix de Guerre and (posthumously) the Congressional Medal of Honor.
Roosevelt was in much demand as a speaker and appeared before many veterans groups and political gatherings. During the period between the world wars, he regularly campaigned throughout the nation for Republican presidential nominees. The Speech, Article, and Book File contains the texts of many such speeches, as well as speech requests and comments. It also contains speeches and other material relating to his role as governor of Puerto Rico, 1929-1932, and governor general of the Philippines, 1932-1933. Roosevelt's many magazine articles of the 1920s and 1930s usually concerned travel, the out-of-doors, or World War I and are preserved in typescript form in the Speech, Article, and Book File. On the other hand, there is little more than correspondence to represent the many books he wrote, although there are drafts, reviews, clippings, legal papers, and research material relating to Eleanor Butler Roosevelt's book, Day Before Yesterday (1959).
The Miscellany file contains a variety of papers, including an autograph collection, items relating to the Roosevelt family, and typewritten transcripts of many letters from Theodore Roosevelt, Sr. and Jr., and Eleanor Butler Roosevelt. A fairly complete file of clippings on the activities of the two Theodore Roosevelts is located among the Printed Matter. Since the clippings are unmounted and in poor condition, photocopies are available for reader use.
Organization of the Papers
The collection is arranged in ten series:
Diaries, 1921-1933
Family Correspondence, 1858-1962
General Correspondence, 1915-1960
Special orrespondence, 1898-1960
Letters of Condolence nd Congratulation, 1934-1949
Subject File, 1917-1959
Speech, Article, and Book File, 1919-1960
Miscellany, 1780-1960
Printed Matter, 1894-1959
Papers of Theodore Roosevelt (1858-1919), 1876-1918
Container List
- Diaries, 1921-1933 (Box 1-2)
  Handwritten diaries and typescripts of diaries.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1921-1923, (3 vols.) (Box 1)
  - 1923-1933, (6 vols.) (Box 2)
- Family Correspondence, 1858-1962 (Box 3-10)
  Letters sent and received.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent and chronologically therein.
  - Alexander family, 1858-1861, 1962, undated (Box 3)
  - Cowles, Anna Roosevelt, 1921-1924
  - Derby, Ethel Roosevelt and Richard, 1923-1959
  - Longworth, Alice Roosevelt, 1929, 1939, undated
  - McMillan, Grace Roosevelt, 1924-1959, undated
  - McMillan, William and Eleanor, 1941-1959, undated
  - McMillan, William, to Theodore Roosevelt, Jr., 1936-1940
  - Miscellaneous family members, 1869-1953
  - Robinson, Mrs. Douglas, 1920-1921, undated
  - Roosevelt, Archibald, to Theodore Roosevelt, Jr., 1920-1944
  - Roosevelt, Belle and Kermit, 1918-1953, undated
  - Roosevelt, Cornelius
    - 1922-1941, (2 folders)
    - 1942-1955, (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Roosevelt, Edith Kermit Carow
    - To Eleanor Butler Roosevelt, 1910-1945, undated
    - To Theodore Roosevelt, Jr.
      - 1897-1932, (2 folders)
      - 1933-1944, undated, (6 folders) (Box 5)
  - Roosevelt, Eleanor Butler
    - 1917-1919, (2 folders)
    - 1925-1943, (8 folders) (Box 6)
    - 1944-1953 (Box 7)
  - Roosevelt, Emlin, to Theodore Roosevelt, Jr., 1941-1942
  - Roosevelt, George Emlin, to Theodore Roosevelt, Jr., 1919-1924
  - Roosevelt, Kermit, to Theodore Roosevelt, Jr., 1921-1941, undated
  - Roosevelt, Quentin, to Eleanor Butler Roosevelt, 1917-1918
  - Roosevelt, Theodore (1858-1919)
    - To Grace Roosevelt Alexander, 1911-1918
    - To Theodore Roosevelt, Jr.
      - 1890-1910, (2 folders)
      - 1911-1918, (3 folders) (Box 8)
  - Roosevelt, Theodore (1887-1944)
    - 1894-1927, (4 folders)
    - 1932-1942, (7 folders) (Box 9)
    - 1943-1944, (5 folders) (Box 10)
  - Roosevelt, Theodore, III, 1938-1960, (3 folders)
  - Roosevelt, Theodore, IV, 1951-1960
- General Correspondence, 1915-1960 (Box 11-25)
  Letters received, with enclosures, and copies of letters sent.
  Arranged chronologically by year and alphabetically by name of correspondent therein.
  - 1915-1920, (8 folders) (Box 11)
  - 1921-1922, (8 folders) (Box 12)
  - 1923-1924 "H", (7 folders) (Box 13)
  - 1924 "I"-1926 "L", (8 folders) (Box 14)
  - 1926 "M"-1927, (6 folders) (Box 15)
  - 1928-1931, (8 folders) (Box 16)
  - 1932, (7 folders) (Box 17)
  - 1933-1934 "B", (5 folders) (Box 18)
  - 1934 "C"-"R", (6 folders) (Box 19)
  - 1934 "S"-1935 "M", (7 folders) (Box 20)
  - 1935 "N"-1936 "M", (7 folders) (Box 21)
  - 1936 "N"-1937, (7 folders) (Box 22)
  - 1938-1939 "S", (8 folders) (Box 23)
  - 1939 "T"-1941 "S", (8 folders) (Box 24)
  - 1941 "T"-1960 (Box 25)
  - Undated
  - Unidentified
  - Fragments
  - Miscellany
- Special Correspondence, 1898-1960 (Box 26-31)
  Correspondence of Theodore Roosevelt Jr., and Eleanor Butler Roosevelt with prominent individuals and friends.
  - Ackerson, George, 1930 (Box 26)
  - Alsop, Corinne, 1937-1938 See also Container 37, Gubernatorial campaign
  - Alsop, Joseph, 1936-1937, undated
  - Alsop, Stewart, 1936-1942, undated
  - Auslander, Joseph, 1939
  - Balfour, Arthur J., 1921
  - Bancroft, Philip, 1920-1941 See also Container 36, American Legion
  - Baruch, Bernard, 1919
  - Belloc, Hilaire, 1936
  - Berlin, Irving, 1940-1946
  - Beston, Henry and Elizabeth, 1919-1957, undated, (6 folders)
  - Beverly, James R., 1931-1941 (Box 27)
  - Borah, William E., 1923-1935
  - Borglum, Gutzon, 1940
  - Bradley, Omar, 1944-1953, undated
  - Bridges, Styles, 1935-1936
  - Buck, Pearl S., 1939-1941
  - Burroughs, John, undated
  - Byrd, Richard E., 1923-1940
  - Byrnes, James F., 1924
  - Carver, George W., 1941
  - Castle, William R., 1931-1941
  - Chiang Kai-shek, and May-ling Soong Chiang, 1938-1940
  - Coffin, Robert P. T., 1937-1943
  - Coolidge, Calvin, 1919-1928
  - Coontz, R. E., 1923-1927 See also Container 37, Gubernatorial campaign
  - Crockett, Cary I., 1930-1946
  - Curtis, Charles, 1921
  - Davis, Benjamin O., 1955
  - Davis, Dwight F., 1923-1932
  - Dempsey, Jack, 1938
  - Denby, Edwin, 1921-1923
  - Dern, George H., 1933
  - De Valera, Eamonn, 1939
  - Dewey, Thomas E., 1935-1953
  - Donald, W. H., 1937-1941
  - Douglas, Benjamin W., 1936-1938
  - Early, Stephen, 1930-1939 (Box 28)
  - Eisenhower, Dwight D. and Mamie, 1944-1960
  - Fareham, Lord Arthur Lee and Lady Ruth, 1921-1940
  - Ferber, Edna, 1938
  - Frankfurter, Felix, 1938-1939
  - Frost, Robert, 1930-1937
  - Gibson, Hugh, 1938-1942
  - Gompers, Samuel, 1923
  - Goodman, Lester, 1934-1938
  - Grey, Sir Edward, 1924-1933
  - Gunther, John, 1922
  - Hand, Learned, 1920
  - Harding, Warren G., 1919-1922
  - Hayes, Helen, 1939-1956
  - Hays, Will, 1939-1941 See also Container 36, American Legion and Election Campaign of Leonard Wood
  - Head, Walter W., 1924-1938
  - Hilles, Charles D., 1926-1937
  - Hoover, Herbert, 1926-1960
  - Hoover, J. Edgar, 1936
  - Hughes, Charles Evans, 1919 See also Container 39, Washington Conference
  - Hunt, William P., 1934-1940
  - Hurley, Patrick J., 1924-1932
  - Hutchins, Robert, 1938-1939
  - Ickes, Harold, 1921
  - Johnson, Hiram, 1922-1923
  - Johnson, James Weldon, 1923-1928
  - Kiernan, John, 1928-1944
  - Kipling, Rudyard, 1930-1935
  - Knox, Frank
    - 1919-1930
    - 1931-1938 (Box 29)
  - Landon, Alf M., 1936-1940
  - Langley, Samuel P., 1898
  - Leary, John J., 1930-1934
  - Leopold of Belgium, 1933
  - Lindsay, Vachel, 1919-1928
  - Lippmann, Walter, 1932-1934
  - Lodge, Henry Cabot (1850-1924) and Lodge, Henry Cabot (1902-1985) 1919-1924, 1932-1934 See also Container 39, Washington Conference
  - Lowden, Frank O., 1919-1927
  - MacArthur, Douglas, 1931-1937
  - MacNider, Hanford, 1920-1934 See also Container 38, Republican Service League
  - McVay, Charles, Jr., 1923-1928
  - Maher, John G., 1918-1931
  - Marquardt, Frederic, 1933-1935
  - Marshall, George C., Jr., 1920-1952 See also Container 37, Gubernatorial campaign
  - Marx, Harpo, 1940
  - Masefield, John, undated
  - Maugham, William Somerset, 1928-1945
  - Mead, Margaret, 1935
  - Mencken, Henry L., 1934-1941
  - Meyer, Eugene L., 1936
  - Miller, Alice Duer, undated
  - Mills, Ogden L., 1926-1932
  - Mitchell, William, 1927
  - Muñoz-Marin, Muna Lee de, 1930-1933
  - Nevins, Allan, 1928
  - Newton, Walter H., 1929-1930
  - Nixon, Richard and Patricia, 1955-1959
  - O'Laughlin, John Collar, 1926-1936
  - Palmer, Frederick, 1929-1940
  - Parker, Frank, 1918-1933
  - Pegler, Westbrook, 1936-1947 (Box 30)
  - Pershing, John J., 1923-1928
  - Pinchot, Gifford, 1921-1933
  - Pound, Ezra, circa 1930s
  - Quezon, Manuel, 1932-1940
  - Richards, Laura E., 1941
  - Richey, Lawrence, 1931-1934
  - Roberts, Kenneth, 1923-1935
  - Robinson, Edwin Arlington, 1930
  - Robinson, Kenneth, 1941
  - Rogers, Will, 1927-1928
  - Romulo, Carlos, 1932-1937
  - Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1910, 1924-1943
  - Roosevelt, Franklin D., 1933-1939
  - Root, Elihu, 1922-1935
  - Ruth, Babe, 1937
  - Sassoon, Siegried, 1937
  - Sibelius, Jean, 1949
  - Sinclair, H. F., 1910-1920
  - Slemp, C. Bascom, 1920-1940 See also Container 37, Gubernatorial campaign
  - Smith, C. Fox, 1930, 1937
  - Spangler, Harrison E., 1935
  - Stearns, F. W., 1926
  - Stefansson, Vilhjalmur, 1922-1939
  - Stein, Aurel, 1930-1934
  - Stettinius, Edward R., Jr., 1935
  - Stimson, Henry L., 1921-1937
  - Stoddard, Lothrop, 1922
  - Storm, Marian, 1938-1939
  - Strauss, Lewis L., 1941
  - Street, Julian, 1920-1941
  - Sullivan, Mark, 1921-1937
  - Taft, Robert A. (1889-1953), 1936-1939
  - Taft, William Howard, 1920
  - Thomas, Norman, 1948
  - Thomason, John W., 1927-1942
  - Tobin, Richard, 1923-1934
  - Truman, Harry S., 1947
  - Tunney, Gene, 1927
  - Vallee, Rudy, 1937
  - Vandenberg, Arthur H., 1932-1936
  - Wallace, Henry C., 1923
  - Weeks, John W., 1922-1924
  - Wells, H. G., 1937-1939
  - West, James E., 1919-1941
  - Wharton, Edith, 1927-1937 (Box 31)
  - White, Stewart E., 1911-1941
  - White, Walter, 1923-1929
  - White, William Allen, 1921-1940
  - Wilbur, Curtis, 1924-1926
  - Wilder, Thornton, 1936-1939
  - Willkie, Wendell L., 1939-1940
  - Wister, Owen, 1921-1933
  - Wood, Eric F., 1920-1940 See also Container 36, Election campaign of Leonard Wood
  - Wood, Leonard. See Container 36, Election campaign of Leonard Wood
  - Woollcott, Alexander, 1935-1943, (2 folders)
  - Wright, Orville, 1927
- Letters of Condolence and Congratulation, 1934-1949 (Box 32-35)
  Letters of congratulation to Theodore and Eleanor Butler Roosevelt on the marriage of their daughter, Grace, to William McMillan, and condolence letters to Eleanor Butler Roosevelt on the death of her husband, and her son Quentin.
  Arranged alphabetically and chronologically. Replies and telegrams have been separated regarding Grace Roosevelt's marriage.
  - Condolence on death of Theodore Roosevelt, Jr., 1944 (Box 32)
    - A-E, (4 folders)
    - F-R, (6 folders) (Box 33)
    - S-Z, (3 folders) (Box 34)
  - Condolence on death of Quentin Roosevelt, 1948-1949
    - A-G, (6 folders)
    - L-Y, (3 folders) (Box 35)
  - Congratulations on wedding of Grace Roosevelt McMillan, 1934, (8 folders)
- Subject File, 1917-1959 (Box 36-39)
  Correspondence, supplemented by reports, transcriptions, copies of speeches, and printed material.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject and chronologically therein.
  - American Legion, founding of, 1919 See also Container 26, Bancroft, Philip; Container 28, Hays, Will (Box 36)
  - Baseball team, Oyster Bay, N.Y., 1937-1940
  - Censorship, World War II, 1958-1959
  - Death of Theodore Roosevelt (1887-1944), radio announcements, 1944
  - Election campaign of Leonard Wood, 1919-1920 See also Container 28, Hays, Will; Container 31, Wood, Eric F.; Wood, Leonard
  - Expeditions
    - Africa, 1939
    - China, 1924-1927, (2 folders)
    - Indo-China, 1926-1936, (2 folders)
    - Java (Rhinoceros Sondaicus), 1934-1939
  - Gubernatorial campaign, 1924 See also Container 26, Alsop, Corinne; Container 27, Coontz, R. E.; Container 29, Marshall, George C.; Container 30, Slemp, C. Bascom (Box 37)
    - Post-election correspondence, (4 folders)
    - Miscellaneous notations
  - Herzfeld, Ernst, 1934-1938
  - Howard University, Washington, D.C., 1920-1931
  - National Conference on Recreation, 1924-1927, (2 folders) (Box 38)
  - New York state, legislation, 1920
  - Republican Service League, 1924-1928 See also Container 29, MacNider, Hanford
  - Socialists' trial, Albany, N.Y., 1920, (2 folders)
  - Teapot Dome investigation, 1924, (2 folders) (Box 39)
  - Washington Conference, "The Limitation of Armanent," 1921-1922 See also Container 28, Hughes, Charles Evans; Container 29, Lodge, Henry Cabot (1850-1924), 1919
  - World War I, papers concerning Roosevelt's service, 1917-1932, (2 folders)
  - World War II, papers concerning Roosevelt's service, 1942-1951
- Speech, Article, and Book File, 1919-1960 (Box 40-54)
  Holograph, typewritten, and bound volumes of speeches, with related correspondence, followed by articles and material relating to Day Before Yesterday by Eleanor Butler Roosevelt.
  Arranged chronologically or alphabetically within categories.
  - Speech File, 1919-1944 (Box 40-49)
    - By Eleanor Butler Roosevelt (Box 40)
      - Comments on speeches, 1940-1941
      - Speeches, "Marriage as a Career," and "American Character," 1940-1944
    - By Theodore Roosevelt (1887-1944)
      - Correspondence
        - Comments on speeches
          - General
            - 1919-1934, (11 folders)
            - 1935-1941, (6 folders) (Box 41)
          - New York State Republican Convention keynote address, 1927, (2 folders) (Box 42)
          - Philippine inaugural address, 1932, (2 folders)
          - Radio broadcast from Manila, Philippines, 1932
          - Second message to Philippine legislature, 1932
        - Requests for speeches
          - 1919-1924, (6 folders)
          - 1925-1935, (9 folders) (Box 43)
          - 1936-1941, (6 folders) (Box 44)
      - Speeches (Box 45)
        - Bound
          - 1920-1924
          - 1924-1928 (Box 46)
          - Philippine statements and speeches, 1932-1933 (Box 47)
          - Puerto Rico statements and speeches, 1929-1933
        - Unbound (Box 48)
          - 1920-1936, (9 folders)
          - 1936-1941, (6 folders) (Box 49)
  - Article File, 1919-1943 (Box 50-51)
    - By Eleanor Butler Roosevelt, 1926-1943, undated (Box 50)
    - By Theodore Roosevelt (1887-1944)
      - Correspondence, 1919-1938, (3 folders)
      - Handwritten drafts